OK, I think we can get started.
Today is lecture 9.
Looks like the attendance is still OK, a bit dropping, not too bad for the weather.
Hopefully that's not because people are not interested.
We're going to cover some more exciting topics, ISA and micro architecture.
Last week we started ISA as you know.
Today we're going to cover some of the trade-offs and I'll give you a big picture also before we
jump into the trade-offs.
And then we all finally start implementing the ISA based on everything we've seen so far using logic
blocks.
And that's going to be our micro architecture.
And we'll look at many different types of micro architectures to implement.
But remember that you have an extra credit assignment if you want to and the deadlines coming up.
And this is kind of the agenda that we have for today.
And the next few lectures, there's ISA, we're going to cover, MIPS, assembly we're going to talk
about.
But I'm going to refer you to another lecture because you all know programming, there's going to be
another type of programming that you're going to do, especially in the labs.
But you've already seen a lot of assembly.
Actually.
This is going to give you a bigger picture of the assembly process.
OK.
What have you been learning?
Hopefully you've seen all of this by now.
We talked about instruction set architectures, instruction formats, clear the von Neumann model
before that, and addressing modes, data types, etcetera.
All sounds good, Everybody's happy.
You know, all of these.
That's good.
And you have some readings.
You can look.
You can look and follow them if you want.
OK, Just to jog your memory, we've been talking about instruction processing cycle.
Instruction cycle, not to be confused with clock cycle.
If you remember, clock cycle is something timing related.
Instruction processing cycle is what stages an instruction goes to be processed in a machine.
And we talk about the six stages of the instruction processing cycle.
We're going to see this more and more as we build our machines, but recall that I've also introduced
you to a part of the finite state machine that we're going to build later today and tomorrow.
Essentially, A finite state machine implements the instruction processing cycle.
And we have seen that on the LC3B finite state machine, there's a full finite state machine that
executes the instructions specified by LC3B.
And you can see that the fetch phase, decode phase, execute phases here.
I will not go through this in detail because we've seen all this happens.
So you have 3 states for fetch and you know our fetch happens by now.
You put the program counter into the memory address register and then increment the program counter
so that points to the next instruction.
We were following the von Neumann model and the memory queries.
Memory is queried and the data appears on the memory data register at after some point and in the
next you you keep transitioning between these States and you transition to the next state when the
data is ready.
At that point, you take the data value in the memory data register, put in the instruction register.
That's how you fetch an instruction.
Must jog your memory, right?
So there's no magic over here.
And you can do all of those in the LC3B or LC3 machine that's designed for this purpose.
We're going to design this in more detail later, OK?
But these are the concepts that we've seen, finite state machine logic blocks and instruction
processing cycle.
So we kind of tied these together, right?
Let's let me just finish this in, in the decode state, state 4, the machine decode the instruction
by looking at the up code using a decoder and then it determines the next state based on that up
code.
OK.
If the up code is a jump, for example, you go to the state.
If you up code is a load, you go to the state.
If you up code is an add, you go to the state.
OK.
That's how you determine what to do based on an instruction.
You go to different state based on the instruction.
So in this case the instruction register the opcode and the instruction registers an input to the
finite state machine.
So it's very, you can connect the concepts, right that we have designed in, in earlier lectures when
we talk about sequential logic on finite state machines.
So there's nothing magic essential.
We're executing an instruction using a finite state machine and this is a full finite state machine
for us to study a bit later.
OK.
So again, just to jog your memory, we've looked at different instructions in LC3 and MIPS
instructions and architectures.
These architectures are relatively similar to each other actually, but one is a toy architecture,
the other is a more real architecture.
We've looked at instructions, up codes, we've looked at data types.
Remember the clock example?
I like that one.
And you can.
You can also think about which data type is.
Natural to humans, right?
Humans also operate on data types.
Actually, some are, some are more natural, some are less natural, but you can get trained to operate
on different data types potentially, right?
Like as opposed to looking at a clock that looks like this, that's easier to read 1420 maybe I
encoded in AI don't know hexadecimal system and I can immediately realise what that is, right?
But humans are easier with decimal.
The question is, is that nature or nurture?
It's a good question also, right?
How are we, are we trained to operate on decimal in general, or can we be trained to do something
else?
Right?
It's good to ask these questions because these are very fundamental and they're going to affect the
nature of humanity going into the future.
Also, if you think about it.
So you may think that this lecture, oh, it's this guy in front of you is making fun of things,
trying to explain you something.
But this sort of stuff is going to be critical to a lot of things in the world, including economies,
wars, and everything.
You can, you can come back to me in 50 years and tell me I'm wrong.
OK, so addressing modes, we've discovered all of that.
Also.
This is basically how do you actually address the operands that you want and operate instructions.
We've covered that.
We've covered data moment instructions and addressing modes.
Especially for data moment instructions, because data moment happens from memory and to memory,
their data addressing modes become very interesting.
Control flow instructions change the sequence of execution, right?
So if you've covered all of this, hopefully you're comfortable with this.
In the assembly programming lecture, you're going to see more of that.
You've covered conditional control flow, which is conditional branching.
So there's a lot more to cover on Isas.
I'm going to cover a little bit more before I, but before that, I'll give you a higher level picture
of program execution.
This is just to give you a higher level picture.
We're not going to be able to cover everything that happens here, but this higher level picture is
important because the question is basically you write a program.
How do you compile and run that program on a machine, right?
There are multiple steps that the program needs to go through.
You can write the program in high level code.
You can write the program in assembly code, which is what the assembly programming lecture is going
to be about.
If you start with a high level code, there is a compiler that takes the program and compiles into
assembly code.
Basically it generates the assembly instructions.
I'm going to show you some examples, but you've seen that also earlier.
And then if you're writing an assembly code, you directly enter from here as a programmer, then
you're an assembly programmer as opposed to high level programmer.
Most high level programmers don't even see this, right?
They should not be computer scientists.
They should be programmers here.
You're you're here for a computer science degree.
That's why you're seeing this, right?
A lot of people don't even know what happens.
It's magic.
Like underneath, I write a program, it magically executes.
Sounds great, and people don't even question how it executes, right?
So this is part of the magic, let's say the mystified, but you know this, it's just putting things
together.
So if you actually write assembly code, there's an assembler which assembles the program into
machine code essentially, right?
That's the idea, although it's not directly machine code because there's some somethings else that
needs to happen.
Assemble actually takes the program and produce an object file that's essentially the program with
some information like symbol table associated with it.
Because you don't know exactly where this program should go.
You don't know exactly what locations the memory addresses are.
They are determined and, and actually the process is a little bit more complicated because you may
actually your program may be calling some library in the operating system, for example, or
something else, though you need to actually, that's somebody else's program and that's somebody
else's program needs to be linked to your program, right?
So there needs to be multiple programs or pieces linked together.
That's why there's another step after the assembler so that you can actually take your object file
and have other object files and put them together, link them in some way such that you create an
executable and that executable actually has the instruction.
I'm going to show you pictures also.
That executable gets loaded into memory and once you load it into memory, you point the program
counter to the beginning of that program.
OK, in MIPS, you know that location 004000 something, right?
I, I always forget.
You don't need to remember anyway as a programmer.
But that gets loaded into that location in memory and then the program counter is set there and then
you can execute the program.
OK, so there's no magic over here.
Let me just give you an example.
You know this already because what is stored in memory, instructions and data in MIPS, instructions
are also called text.
There's data.
Data can be global or dynamic.
It could be allocated within program, allocated before program begins.
These are a bit different because it depends on how you address them, right?
Addressing is different, so there's different space in memory allocated for this, different types of
data.
And in MIPS, the memory happens to be only four gigabytes.
You may say this is small.
I agree it's small, but we're going to fix this problem.
In Lecture 2526, when we talk about virtual memory, right, this is actually virtual memory.
Programmer may actually get a lot more memory.
OK, so this is the MIPS memory map.
You don't need to understand everything.
If you want to know really more, I would recommend looking at Harris and Harris Chapter 6.6.
But this is where the program goes.
You can see that that number 004400 thousand in hex.
That's where the program counterpoints.
And your program can be this large, at least in memory, virtual.
With virtual memory, you can do as large as possible.
And then your static data which is allocated in the program goes here.
And then dynamic data, static data which is available before the program starts goes here.
For example, some inputs maybe here and your or some variables that are set to some values are here
and your dynamic data that's allocated within the program.
So if you're dynamically allocating a linked list or array, for example, goes here.
So there are different parts where the data is stored, but both programs and memory are in the same
place.
You can actually have a program over here, instructions over here, and you can jump there, right?
You know that with von Neumann architecture.
OK, so this is an example C code.
I'll not go through the details of it.
It does something.
It computes a sum of two things that are statically allocated.
As you can see, they're given values.
In fact, they're variables, global variables in this case.
And you take the sum and you return the results, right?
The assembly code is this.
You can verify it on your own, but this is so this high level program gets compiled by a compiler to
this assembly code.
OK, that's the assembly code.
You can do it.
You can give it to AI today.
It can do it.
Hopefully, hopefully it won't be wrong, but it should be able to do this.
This is not rocket science, even for AI.
Some things it's good at, some things it may not be very good at, but this thing it should be really
good at, you know, but you can do it also now that you learned MIPS ISA, right?
So there's some things that you do and you, you should watch the assembly programming lecture to
figure out how to do it better.
OK, that's assembly code.
And then this gets, let me go back to over here, This gets assembled into an object file.
I will not go through the object file in detail, but essentially here you can see that there are
variables over here, right?
For example, there's Y, there's G, there's F.
But in machine code there are no such things.
We need to allocate addresses to them, right?
So we need to be able to do that addresses.
So there's some symbol table that allocates addresses.
For example, this says main should start from this location where the PC should point to.
That's the beginning of the program sum, which is a function should start from this location in
memory.
And these are the global variables that are in the global part of the main memory where the
variables are.
So somebody needs to do that allocation of addresses to variables.
And that's what the assembler does and produces a symbol table and supplies it to the next level,
which is the linker.
And the linker essentially fixes all the addresses, including some addresses that may be coming from
some other programs that you call or some other operating system functions that you may call, which
we're not going to get into today, but later we may get into.
And essentially produces this executable.
An executable is some format where there's a header.
The header specifies some things like text size, data size, etcetera.
And then the next segment, there's a text segment, which is really the program over here with all of
the addresses fixed.
And then there's a data segment over here, OK, with with it, with the symbol table.
And then this program gets loaded into memory using all of this information in the executable,
because executable exactly specifies at which address what data you have, right?
So that's what happens.
So this is the, we're going back to the memory map program goes here, static data goes here in in
this program, we don't have dynamic data.
So it looks like this program goes here, you start from PC and then you start executing sequentially
unless there's a control flow change.
And these are the variables, OK.
And this is machine code.
Basically this is all the formats of the instructions and coding.
This is what goes to memory.
So hopefully this is a bit demystified right now and you'll learn more from the assembly programming
lecture as to how that machine code is generated from assembly.
You'll do these in your labs also.
So it's good to study this in my opinion, for your labs.
Sounds good.
How many of you have programmed the assembly so far?
OK, not many.
How many have not?
OK, that's good.
You're in for fun.
No, no, this is where actually the data goes static.
Essentially static variables go there.
Exactly.
There should be some actual values.
Yeah.
Initialized to values.
Your, your book didn't do a perfect job over there.
Maybe.
Yeah, yeah.
Or they could be.
Yeah, exactly.
They should be actual values.
Good question.
OK, so now that I've given you the big picture, hopefully you understand the entire process.
We're going to switch gears to ISA trade-offs a little bit more because ISA is very important in
design.
Every computer needs an ISA, some sort of essentially ISA is the hardware software interface, right?
What kind?
How do you actually communicate with this machine?
Every computer has an ISA.
It may not be exactly like this ISA that we have seen.
And I'm going to challenge you and think about, hopefully one of the key goals of this course is
think critically, right?
Not take anything as a given, and we're going to think critically and think about different types of
Isas, right?
In the end, every computer, people are very Gaga about quantum computing today, for example, right?
If you design A quantum computer, you have to communicate with the software.
This quantum computer will not magically figure out what people will do.
So in a quantum computer, in fact, people are proposing Isas that are very similar to what today's
Isas are.
But maybe they should be thinking bigger in how to actually exploit quantum computers, which may
happen 30 years down the road, or may not happen, We don't know.
Maybe 100 years down the road, if the Earth doesn't explode by then anyway.
But it's good to keep in mind that whatever computer you design, you have to communicate with it,
right?
And there needs to be an ISA.
Maybe it's going to be human language, but underneath there needs to be some ISA that the human
language gets translated to, right?
It's good to think about these things.
So I'm going to cover some more ISA trade-offs, which we started a little bit in the last lecture.
A key trade off in an ISA is how complex or simple should your instructions, data types and
addressing modes be?
If it's a complex instruction, this means that an instruction does a lot of work, meaning it does
many operations.
For example, it could be matrix multiply, right?
That's that's a pretty complex instruction.
It could be a convolution, which we're going to see in lecture 16 or so.
That's a pretty complex instruction.
It's could be fast Fourier transform, compute that thing, right?
Or do insert into a doubly linked list, or insert into a 10 dimensional array or, or query in a
database, right?
These are pretty high level concepts, right?
String copy is relatively high level also, but you could actually go even higher level.
So simple instructions on the other hand, are more primitive instructions, operations.
An instruction does little work.
It's a primitive using which complex operations can be built.
And you've seen you can have NAND, for example, right?
NAND is a simple instruction, add, XOR, multiply, multiply is a little bit more complex, a more
complex primitive shift, for example, jump.
It's good to think about.
Can you have a single instruction that can do everything that we discussed?
I'm not going to talk about that right now, but it's a good thought exercise.
Maybe can you have a single instruction ISA and write all the programs that you can write today?
So there's a basically you're faced with a fundamental trade-offs immediately when you're designing
an ISA.
You can of course say, I want both complex and simple.
Then your ISA is pretty complex, right?
Because you actually want to implement everything.
So why does this matter?
You've seen this also.
This is called the semantic gap.
Actually, you've seen that high level language, you get compiled to assembly or machine code
eventually, right?
Essentially, you have an high level language people are used to programming with.
Most people don't program with machine code.
Yeah, actually assembly, most people don't program with assembly code.
Even fewer people program with machine code.
Basically almost nobody.
But essentially how how complex your instructions, data types and addressing modes R determines the
semantic gap between your high level language, Java, C++, Python, pick your favorite and the ISA
hardware software interface.
If these are complex.
If you have many data types, for example data types.
For example a matrix is a data type, right?
Integers are data type, integers are more primitive, but matrix is a collection of integers that are
laid out in a particular way.
2 dimensional right?
You can have 10 dimensional a race that could be also data types, right?
Those are pretty complex data types at a high level.
A database itself could be a data type, for example, right?
Of course you need to specify a bit more to get it implemented.
But essentially if these are very high level, you have a very small semantic gap.
And if these are low level, meaning less complex, you have very few data types, simple things, then
you have a large semantic gap.
And this actually determines a lot of trade-offs.
For example, if these are high level, the compiler's job may be easier, right?
You can more easily map high level language to the ISA.
Potentially it's less work for the software designer.
But then there's a big gap over here.
And what does this gap mean?
You have these instructions and you need to build a machine that executes them, right?
That's what I specify.
The hardware control signals, control signals.
We're going to see a lot more.
You've seen control signals and data signals.
Control signals determine what the machine does every clock cycle.
Basically, you have some set of control signals, right?
Every state in a finite state machine generates a control signal.
For example, one control signal is what should the ALU do in this state?
What should the which?
What should be loaded onto the bus in the state, for example.
So if the ISA is very high level, that gap is huge.
As a result, hardware designer's job is harder.
OK, so this is the hardware software interface.
If you think about the blue line, if this part is small, software designer's job is easier, hardware
designer's job is harder.
Whereas on, in this case, this is large, meaning software designer needs to do more to get from very
high level to very primitive operations.
But the hardware designer doesn't need to do as much probably because they only need to implement
primitive operations, right?
They don't need to deal with a matrix multiply, for example.
So this is going to be a very critical trade off that will affect us a lot, especially when we talk
about execution models.
We'll talk about systolic arrays, we'll talk about GPU SIMD execution, we'll talk about VLIW.
And people have been trying to tackle this trade off and there is no escape.
In the end, you make this trade off, you can say I want both.
Yes, people have done that also because existing complex ISA is actually both in the end.
They don't forego NAND instructions for example.
They still have those instructions, but that's why they're more complex in hardware.
So basically here the optimization burden is also on hardware because there is a huge gap.
Optimization opportunity here is lower because of that small gap, whereas here the optimization
burden is on the software because software does a lot of the high level language to ISA
translation.
OK, it's good to think about that also, right?
Who does the optimization, right?
OK, and it's also good to think about here the hardware is more complex.
In the end here the hardware is simple.
So a complex instructions make hardware more complex.
Simple instructions make hardware simpler.
But for software it becomes the opposite, especially if you want optimised programs.
OK, OK.
I'm spending some time over here because it's going to be important.
So people have also thought about a lot of interesting things like changing the trade-offs that you
have.
For example, here you have an ISA that's very close to high level language and you have your
hardware is normally complex.
But if you insert something in the middle, meaning this is the programmer visible ISA, and you also
have some other instructions that's implementation ISA, that's much simpler.
Now you can change the trade-offs a little bit, right?
So there's one blue line over here that's visible to the programmer or the compiler.
And this blue line instructions that are not visible to the programmer.
This is the hardware designer decides this.
And these are simple, but these are complex.
So the programmer compiles into something complex, but then that complex thing gets translated into
something simple.
And then the question becomes who does that translation, right.
So that could become either software or hardware.
That's the fascinating part.
Basically, we call this ISA, the hardware software interface, but not exactly right?
You can translate that to something else later on in software or hardware as well.
So this is fascinating because now we have an indirection that you've added, you can change the
trade off significantly.
So this is actually done in essentially all general purpose processors today.
You compile into a very complex ISA today, X86.
It's one of the more most complicated ISA that is developed, but you can translate it into something
else internal.
Actually, that's not exactly what's done in existing processors.
This is something else.
This is what Apple's Rosetta 2 binary translator does.
What they do is basically they can also execute X86 code over here, but so X86 programs get
translated to the ARM ISA, which the processor is actually implemented with.
And that translation software is a translation software is a software basically with some hardware
support to make it faster and easier.
OK, so that's how they can execute programs that are not compatible with the hardware software
interface of.
Processor, you can design processor with some ISA, but you can execute programs written for some
other ISA.
OK, that's enables, that's enabled through this translation mechanism.
It's also called binary translation.
OK, so hopefully that's interesting.
This is different from a compiler.
Of course, the binary translator can optimise the code also, so it can do some of the compiler's
tasks.
OK, so it's done in real machines.
Intel and AMD machines do something different.
They basically take X86 code and they they translated into using hardware secret micro operations.
These are basically some implementation ISA that is with simpler instructions.
They basically don't want to do expensive, don't want to implement very expensive operations like
string copy for example.
They divide into smaller pieces that the hardware implements, but this translation actually happens
in hardware, so it's very quick.
OK, but then the hardware is still complex, right, If you think about it, but maybe not as complex
as if you had implemented all of those instructions that are specified by the ISA.
And X86 specifies 1000 plus instructions.
I'm going to show you a picture of the instruction set manual.
It's 5000 plus pages, and that was three years ago.
I don't want to go and find the X86 manual again.
OK, so these are actually real processors do this All real.
All Intel and AMD processors do it.
Other folks also do it, So and media.
For example, they implemented this interesting SoC processor where the instruction set architecture
was ARM, which is actually not as complex as X86, but they still wanted to simplify the hardware.
So they use a software translator to translate the ARM ISA to secret micro operations internally.
And if you're interested you can read more about that.
And they also do dynamic code optimization internally.
So when you translate from one piece of code to another piece of code, they may be written in
different languages.
You can still optimise the code, right?
And you can read more about if you're interested.
OK, this is an old idea.
People have actually tried to do this.
This is this.
How many people have heard about this processor called Transmeta?
No one, maybe some old folks.
OK, nobody.
But this was actually interesting because this is during the heyday of X86 where X86 processors were
dominating the world, which is actually different today, which is why this course is also important
because there's a huge challenge against how we design processors today, right?
People have been designing X86 processors and that was the dominant ISA.
And these folks, these bright folks at Transmeta, they wanted to basically say we want to be compete
with X86 and but we don't want to design these complicated processors because it's expensive and
Intel and AMD have a lot of expertise in designing these processors.
So what we're going to do is we're going to take X86 programs and design something called code
morphing software, which is essentially a binary translator with a lot of code optimization and
translate the ISA to some proprietary ISA that we're going to learn and lecture.
Something I forgot now probably 17 or 14.
Anyway, VLIWISA, which is actually extracting parallelism so you can actually do a lot of operations
in parallel.
And their goal was to actually outperform existing X86 processors using this sort of approach.
Now they didn't succeed, although they were able to produce very energy efficient processors at the
time.
Maybe they were not at the right time on on the market because energy efficiency became much more
important after they kind of died.
So this was a start up that tried to do something different, right?
So trying and failing is good actually because this inspired a lot of approaches later on.
OK, so the bigger principle here is indirection, right?
And essentially some people have said, David Wheeler said any problem in computer science can be
solved with another level of indirection may or may not be true.
But in this particular case, we're using indirection, right?
We have one level of ISA and then we have another level of ISA and we're basically translating.
So once you do that sort of translation or this sort of indirection, trade-offs can change and new
opportunities can become enabled.
You're basically not stuck with a complex instructions that that you have to implement in hardware,
right?
You can actually change the trade-offs if you actually insert some level of indirection.
The problem is this indirection comes with extra complexity and latency always, right?
That code morphing software and that hardware has additional latency.
Certainly.
Now if it optimises the program and it amortises the cost of that latency over many, many
executions, that may be good, but that may not be always possible.
OK, so we'll see this in direction again in Lecture 2526 when we talk about virtual memory where we
will insert.
So, so far we've seen memory addresses, right?
Memory addresses.
Specified by an instruction are physical memory addresses.
Now it turns out that's not a good idea, because physical memory may be limited.
So we'll insert another level of instruction, another level of indirection, where we will turn those
memory addresses specified by the program to virtual memory addresses, and we will translate them
to physical memory addresses in the machine itself.
That idea has been extremely useful, and that's been the dominant way of implementing memory today,
which is virtual memory.
So all of those addresses that you've seen are going to be virtual, meaning they don't exist in
physical space.
They're going to be translated to actual addresses in physical space later on because we want to
give the impression to the programmer that they have infinite memory.
OK, so if you didn't understand anything, hold off until lecture 25.
By that time you will understand virtual memory, but it's going to be the same high level principle
which is indirection.
Sounds good.
OK, so let me give you a couple of other ISA level trade-offs.
There are a lot of trade-offs actually, but I cannot cover everything because we have other things
to cover also.
Number of registers and other trade off, right?
When you design an ISA, assuming that you wanted registers in the ISA, how many registers do you
want to have, right.
This is actually a trade off that you need to decide almost immediately and this effects a lot of
things.
This effects, as you have seen, number of bits used for encoding the register address.
In LC3 we had eight registers, so you had three bits for source register, one source register 2 and
destination register.
So it actually consumes 9 bits in the instruction encoding.
In MIPS, it was 5 bits per register because we had 32 registers that consumes 15 bits instruction
and coin.
So instructions are immediately larger, right?
So it's, it's, it's also affects the number of values kept in fast storage, which is register file.
And we know the importance of this, right?
If you have a lot of variables that you're reusing multiple times in your program, you want more
registers, right?
If your registers, if the number of registers you have is only 8 and if you're using 9 values, 9
variables a lot together, we're going to talk about that later on.
Also, locality principle, then 8 is not enough, right?
You just needed one more register, right?
So the larger is better for reducing accesses to memory so that you don't go go far away to memory
to bring the value and you keep it in fast storage and in the micro architecture level it effects.
If you have a larger structure to hold values, this affects the size of it.
Clearly it's more expensive.
This affects the access time because it takes longer.
You need more, you need a bigger decoder, you need a wider Max.
Remember the memory structure that we designed, You need a bigger decoder, wider Max.
And those increase the latency of all of those structures, right?
Those increase the power consumption also if you have bigger decoders or hierarchy of the
hierarchical decoders as we have seen if you have for example 8 to 1 decoder, yeah, if you're if
you're decoding let's say 3 bits of address versus 5 bits of address, 5 bits of address is
definitely more right in terms of hardware logic.
And this increase the power consumption.
So clearly number of registers immediately effects everything we care about, right.
The problem is it's a trade off.
If you have large number of registers, you have fewer, it enables better registry allocation for
those values that you want to keep close to the the computation unit because you're dealing with a
lot of values.
And this actually leads to fewer accesses to memory, right?
Saves and restores.
If you watch the assembly programming lecture, you will see that also.
So you get better performance with larger number of registers, performance in the sense that you
have fewer accesses to memory, right?
But unfortunately you have larger instruction size which also affects your performance as we will
see.
Because this occupies now when you actually get your instructions from memory into the processor,
you need to fetch more things, right, Bigger things.
So that affects your performance also.
And you have a larger register file size, meaning your register file may take longer to access.
So clearly the first part, enabling better allocation in the registers or number of values kept in
fast storage gets you better performance.
But these two get you lower performance potentially.
In general, this is better because going to memory is very expensive and the benefit that you get by
not going to memory by having more registers overcomes the downsides, performance downsides of
this, but there are also energy and power consumption.
So we already saw this trade off somewhat in LC3 versus MIPS, right, Three bits versus 5 bits.
But keep this in mind essentially, OK, I don't want to cover more trade-offs in ISA because I want
to cover something bigger, which is a trade off in ISA, but not this is if you think about it, this
is a more, I don't want to call it a micro level trade off because it's important.
This is once you determine the execution model, this is an important trade off that you need to
think about.
But then there's a bigger thing that we may want to think about when we talk about Isas.
I'm going to show you these things.
If you're interested in learning more about Isas, we'd like to do a little bit more critical
thinking in designing Isas because maybe the execution model that we designed is not that great and
it's good to think about that, right?
OK, So what do you, what do I mean by that?
We talked about the von Neumann model, which is a great model, no question about that because it's
very easy to think about.
I think you have a stored program instructions that are data packed in that program.
And then you do sequential instruction processing, which is it's really the hallmark of von Neumann
model.
So I've already said the stored program memory is unified between instructions and data and the
interpretation of a stored value depends on the control signals.
We discussed this just to jog your memory.
When is the value interpreted as an instruction?
Basically, it depends on when that address is accessed in the instruction processing cycle or which
state in your finite state machine do you access the address?
OK, so in the fetch state you generate a memory address.
You go to that memory address and get something and put it in the instruction register.
That means that you've interpreted that thing in memory as an instruction.
OK, you could have access any part of memory.
As long as you point the PC to that part, you're going to get that as an instruction, right?
Which means that if you actually point PC to the wrong part, and the thing that you get doesn't
encode is not a valid encoding of an instruction, the machine will try to execute something that is
not an instruction and it will generate an exception saying that this is not an instruction, right?
It'll bar for you, meaning it'll stop, right?
We'll see exceptions later on.
OK, so that's the fetch state.
If you actually access memory in this fetch operand state, which is actually implemented as a state
in the finite state machine.
When you're implementing the machine, you interpret the memory value of the data, meaning you get
the address, you put it in the memory address register, and the memory responds in the memory data
register.
And that data goes to a register, right?
It doesn't go into the instruction register.
It goes into a general purpose register.
Now that data is inside your register file, so you're treating as data.
OK, so that basically resolves the first issue with von Neumann model.
You have a stored program.
You can change that also.
You could think about changing that.
You could basically say I'm never going to be able to access data and instructions, but let's not do
that for now.
Let's talk about sequential instruction processing.
We wanted to discuss this also.
We have a program counter instruction pointer that identifies a current instruction.
And this is advanced sequentially except for control transfer instructions, right?
So that's the von Neumann model that we've discussed.
If you're interested, you can read more.
And we built a lot of things.
The question I want to ask is, is this the only way that a computer can process programs, right?
Anybody.
That sounds good, of course, but I guess some people say no.
OK, basically no.
The qualified answer is basically no.
But it has been the dominant way we build general purpose machines.
OK, dominant paradigm for computing.
That's why it's been very powerful for N decades, although things that may be changing a little bit
with Fpgas, reconfigurable computing, we'll talk about that a little bit.
So let's examine a complete different model for processing computer program.
This is just one model and it's actually a pretty powerful model, and that's called the data flow
execution model.
Has anyone heard about data flow before?
Yes, maybe some.
OK, so basically if you look at the von Neumann model, an instruction is fetched and executing
control flow order, right?
You have a control flow order that you dictate.
You start from the program counter, you go to program counter, next program counter, next program
counter.
And that's sequential, right?
Basically you're everything is specified by this program counter.
Intel calls an instruction pointer, which is actually a much nicer and much more accurate name,
right?
But counter is also not inaccurate assuming you keep counting, right?
You're really counting except.
When you have a control flow instruction that changes that immediately.
OK, so basically you have sequential execution unless you have an explicit control flow instruction
that takes you to a non sequential place.
Whereas in data flow model an instruction is fetched and execute in data flow order.
Now this may not mean anything.
Hopefully it will mean something soon.
Basically, there is no program counter.
Forget about the program counter.
Program counter is nice because it tells you, OK, I'm at this instruction, but we're critically
thinking, right, why do you need to have a program counter?
Really.
Can you specify programs to execute on machines without having a program counter?
And the answer is yes.
Basically you you derive an execution model where an instruction gets fetched and executed when it's
all parents are ready.
This is data flow because an instruction has inputs and the inputs are the data through the
instruction.
For example, add an add operation has two inputs right as we have seen, and one output whenever both
of its inputs are generated.
You need to keep track of that of course.
Somehow the add instruction gets fetched from its location memory and gets executed.
At that point there is no program counter.
You can do it for every instruction multiply again two operations and not has 122 operands and not
has one operand, right?
Whenever that is ready.
Now, what does ready mean?
If it's actually specified in the program as a variable that's set, it's ready immediately.
If it's generated as an output of another instruction, that instruction needs to have executed first
and made that input operand ready, right?
OK, so that's the idea over here.
Basically, there is no program counter, which means instruction ordering is specified by data flow
dependencies that you have in a program, right?
I'm going to show you an example soon.
Meaning there needs to be some different encoding that you develop to actually enable this model,
right?
Meaning the hardware software interface is quite different.
OK, so each instruction specifies who, meaning which other instructions should receive the result.
So you need to somehow connect the instructions to each other.
And this actually nicely done graphically.
And we're going to do a little bit of graphical programming, if you will.
So an instruction can fire, meaning gets fetched and executed whenever all operands are received,
all its source operands are received.
So there needs to be a model where instructions monitor which operands are ready, right?
OK.
So the key realisation is that you're executing many instructions potentially at a time, right?
You're not limited to program counter.
I have this instruction only.
Many instructions may become ready at the same time and I may be executing all of them at the same
time, assuming I have enough AL use functional units.
So inherently this is more parallel.
You can argue about that, maybe anybody who wants to dispute this, maybe not, but we'll we'll see
some other methods in later lectures where we will try to get parallelism into this sequential
model also.
OK, so inherently this is more parallel because many instructions can be ready at the same time.
There's no program counter dictating you should be at this instruction and you cannot move to the
next instruction until you finish this instruction.
OK, so let's take a look at this pictorial.
You consider a von Neumann programme that looks like this.
I'm not going through the ISA here, but this is more, let's say you can understand this, right?
You have A+B, and then you do BB times 2, and then X gets v -, W, which is the result of these
instructions.
Y gets V + W and Z gets X * y.
So A&B are the inputs here.
Z is the only output.
Everything else is intermediate variables.
So this is sequential also by nature.
This looks very sequential, right?
I've written it that way, so it's good to think about what is the significance of the program order
here, right?
What does it help?
We're going to talk about that later on.
One thing it helps is readability.
Perhaps you can read it nicely sequentially again and maybe you can think more easily about that.
I don't know what is the significance of the storage location.
I kind of already said that, right?
A&B are inputs, Z is the only output.
This W which is going to be assigned A register is an intermediate result, right?
You don't really need it at the end of the program, but it's used as an input to another
instruction.
This V, which is assigned as the output of this instruction is used as the input of this
This X similarly used as the output of this intermediate instruction to for, well, not the, I
shouldn't call it intermediate instruction, this instruction, but it's but it's an intermediate
output.
It's used as the input of this instruction Y also, etcetera.
OK, so this is a data flow program for this thing graphically expressed.
Now, if you look at this may be harder to read, I don't know, but I don't care about the things over
here.
I have three names over here, right?
Abz 2 inputs, 1 output, and I have only operations 4-5 operations just like here, but they're laid
out in a way that's not that where there's no dictation of the program order, right?
There's no order basically over here, except there has to be some order because some instructions
need to be executed before others so that their values are available, right?
Which is a data dependence order.
So this is the same program.
You can convince yourself that this is the same program, hopefully, right?
Do you agree?
OK, I don't need to go through everything here.
OK.
The question, I mean, one, there are many questions that could be asked over here, right?
But one question is which model is more natural to you as a programmer?
Who says the sequential 1?
OK, a lot of hands.
Who says the Dataflow one?
OK, fewer hands.
That's what I expected.
And then the next question to ask is, is it because you are exposed more to this?
It's good to think about that, right?
Or is it because there is an inherent bias in human nature to be more sequential, right?
It's very hard to believe that if you know how well, we don't know exactly how things work.
But if you know the parallelism that exists in brain, maybe our interface is limiting or maybe our
nurture is limiting us.
So it's good to think about that.
So a little bit more, I'll stop at some point soon.
In a data flow machine, a program consists of data flow notes.
So basically I've shown you data flow notes.
This is your program basically, right?
A data flow node fires, it gets fetched and executed when all of its inputs are ready, meaning when
all inputs have tokens.
So we're going to introduce this concept of tokens soon.
And you can actually implement this as an ISA, which is interesting, right?
You can actually translate this thing.
This is a multiply operation.
It has two inputs, argument one and argument 2, and it has one output which is the destination of
the result, right?
The result needs to go somewhere, right?
You need to you specify where does the result go, which note does the result go.
And R is the multiply is the up code over there.
And R is whether the argument one is ready.
And this R is whether argument 2 is ready.
So you need to keep track of the readiness of the operands.
Now, if you look over here, that's one way of actually translating this graphical thing into an ISA.
You could actually do this, or another way of doing this is let's assume that this is your program
and this is what you're going to execute.
You can build this directly in circuits, right?
You could take this graphical thing, put it into your circuit.
You have a design A multiplier.
Design A multiplier by two, which is going to be simpler than your multiplier, which is actually
shift by one, shift left by 1, and then design subtractor and adder another multiplier.
Put all of them on your FPGA.
Then your hardware software interface is something different, right?
It's essentially the bitstream that goes into your FPGA as opposed to something that's more
standardised like this.
OK, so it's good to think about it.
So there you can build actually a full graphical interface for this.
For example, you can have a conditional node.
This is a conditional branch implementation.
So you have a branch, you have an input coming here.
There are two inputs actually.
One is the data input, 1 is the control input.
What a branch node does or get a conditional node does, is if the control input is true, it takes
the data input and passes it into the true path.
If this is false, it takes the data input and passes it through the false path.
The key is this instruction gets fetched and executed when both inputs have tokens, meaning they are
available, OK when they're ready.
OK, OK, relational let's for example this one.
The result will go here X the data value over here goes here, which is connected to another data
flow node.
OK, here relational can determine whether it's something is false or true.
So for example, this relational test greater than if the left node.
So this this instruction or node gets fetched and executed when both the inputs are ready.
If the left input is greater than the right input, the output will have a true token.
Otherwise it will have a false token.
OK, so it can basically implement anything this way.
It's beautiful graphical instruction, right?
I'm not going to talk about barrier synchronisation right now, but you can think about it.
Maybe I'll go through this and some of you may want to look at look over it during the break.
So this is a simple data flow program.
Let me run through it to set the base.
So there are two inputs, 1 here and NN is a non negative integer.
That's important.
Non negative is very important.
And there's an output over here.
OK, so we have a bunch of nodes.
This is a branch node that you have seen over here earlier, right?
It has data, it has a boolean value, and node fires when both values are available and you get the
output when the boolean is false.
This may indicate you something we're going to reverse engineer what this program does.
That's going to be my question to you.
Basically, what does this program do?
What is the value of out basically?
So a couple of things.
This copy node basically copies.
It fires when an input is available over here.
It copies the value in the input to both places.
Basically, it has two destination.
So one of them goes here, which is the input of the branch.
The other goes here, which is whether that value is greater than 0.
And then you test that you get a false or true and then that gets copied.
And that controls these two branches over here, right?
Meaning that if this is false, you're going to get the output.
And also this output over this input over here will kind of die.
This is the this is the death node, if you will, the node.
Basically there is no destination for that token.
That token dies over there.
It gets killed, but that token continues to be alive if this boolean is true.
And if this is boolean true, this also continues to be alive.
OK?
So there's another copy, there's a decrement, there's a multiply.
And then there's this looping, which can be done better.
But the basic idea is when you have a loop, you basically supply another token to another iteration,
let's say, OK, so this one becomes something else in the next time because of this.
And this N becomes something else in the next time, next iteration, let's say.
OK, so basically you keep supplying tokens until this becomes false and you get the out.
The question is what is the value of out after you execute this data flow program?
And this is a great time to take a break.
Let's take a break until 1521 and then maybe, hopefully some of you will have answers to what this
program does.
Anybody figured out what this program is doing?
We have one hand, two hands, three hands.
Raise your hand higher.
OK, more.
More than three hands.
Have you figured out what this program is doing?
OK, good.
Okay du machst.
Many people have not figured out what this program is doing, which is fine.
Don't worry.
How many people tried but did not figure out or tried?
Maybe you figured it out.
OK, OK, So what is this program doing?
Go ahead.
It computes M factorial.
Do the other people agree?
Who says who has a different answer?
OK, I guess those of you who say M factorial win.
So this computes N factorial.
I'll go over this relatively quickly.
But essentially in the beginning you have two tokens, one and N Of course N is not N.
It's not supposed to be some value, but that's the mystery question.
It's let's assume that it's, I don't know 4, right?
Give it a value 4 and try.
4 is non negative.
As far as I know, there's not not been debunked by AI yet.
OK, so you have one over here and you have 4.
Let's say N it one goes to this node.
This node cannot fire because it has one token over here, but it doesn't have the boolean token yet.
So N goes to this node.
This node can fire because it has only one input.
This is remember the next iteration.
So it copies N over here, which is 4.
Let's assume it's 4.
So 4 goes here and four goes here.
This node cannot fire yet because it's it's waiting for the boolean token.
4 is greater than 0, so N is greater than 0 in this case.
So this becomes true.
So now true gets copied, that node fires, and this node fires immediately because there's only one
input.
True gets copied over here.
So this boolean becomes true.
This boolean becomes true, and both nodes fire at the same time because their values were ready.
One was one, the other was 4, which is N so this is true.
So one gets passed over here to the multiply node.
Multiply node cannot fire yet because it's other input is not ready.
This 4 gets passed over here.
This node can fire.
4 gets copied over here.
So four goes here.
4 also goes to the decrement node, 4 -, 1 becomes 3.
So this multiply computes 1 * 4, which is N.
So four goes here.
So it's goes here, right?
This four and this three goes here.
OK, so in the first iteration, if you will be multiplied one with four, one with N if you think
about it in the second and and also decremented N, right?
So we we multiplied one with N and decremented N to become three.
Now in the next iteration, what will happen is essentially the same thing.
If you go through this, because 3 is also greater than 0.
We will multiply whatever here is which is 4/4 by three and that result will go over here and three
will be decremented by one.
This will become two.
OK, so 4 by 3 is 12.
Four times, 3 will come here and 2 will come here.
So this will compute 4 * 3 * 2 in the next iteration, and this will be decremented by 1:00.
We will have one more iteration and also 4 * 3 * 2 will go here, which is 24 by the way.
So we'll have one more iteration where 24 will go here and one is greater than 0, so 1 will come
over here.
You could have prevented that iteration probably.
And you will multiply 24 by 1 and get 24.
At that point in time, in the next iteration, you'll have zero over here, 0 is not greater than 0,
OK, So this boolean will be false.
This boolean will be false.
So 24, which is N factorial will come from this multiply and this is false.
So output will become N factorial.
And this value, which is 0 in the end will die because it will go into this, let's say ground.
OK, so that's a relatively quick explanation.
You could have simulated this more of course, but that's the idea.
Every iteration calculates this input, times this input, and decrements N by 1.
And if you do that, that's N factorial in the end, assuming N is a non negative integer.
OK, so this is one way of implementing N factorial using a graphical data flow program.
You could come up with other implementations.
This is relatively sequential.
There could be better implementations that are parallel.
I'll let you think about that.
OK, so, but this gives you an example that we don't need a program country in ISA, right?
You could directly implement this in an FPGA.
Also, right, all of these can be circuits that are just doing M factorial.
If you want this M factorial program, this is it.
Potentially it may not be very high performance, but it's your program that could be baked into
hardware, so you could get some performance from that.
So do we want a program counter in the ISA?
So if you say yes, that's a very high level trade off.
Basically, if you say yes, you will get control driven sequential execution, which is very similar
to the von Neumann model.
PC automatically changes sequentially.
So that's where the sequentiality comes from, right?
And you're executing 1 instruction at a time, whereas if you say no, you get something else.
And data flow is one example of it.
You get more data-driven, more parallel execution and instructions executed when all its operands
values are available.
And you could actually build a full computing system this way you know everything.
You can view as graphs, you can view the interaction with the IO devices, output input all as
graphs.
So you can, you can think of the world as graphs, right?
And that could be your programming model and interaction model, which is actually a very powerful
way of thinking because it unleashes a lot of parallelism, right?
You're not limiting the parallelism to where the program counter points to you.
Actually, whenever something happens and an instruction becomes ready, beginning its input offends
are ready, you can execute it, OK.
And there could be thousands or millions of instructions that you can execute concurrently that way.
So there are many high level trade-offs.
I'm giving you one.
Ease of programming is another question, of course, right?
For average programmers, which one's easier?
Sequential is in general easier.
But then that is that a, is that a matter of how education systems are built, right.
Whenever you learn programming, you always learn sequential, right?
It's hard to break this vicious cycle.
Maybe if that education continues that way, right?
So it's good to think about that some some people who are actually very good with data flow think
data flow is better, right?
I think a few of you lifted your hands, so it's possible.
Ease of compilation is another question.
I'm not going to go into that, but you can think about it.
Compilers are also easier if they're sequential, right?
Parallel is harder in general.
Performance is another question.
Extraction of parallelism in general, it's a lot.
You can, you can have a lot more operations in parallel available in parallel with the data flow
model.
And that's why people have investigated this very, very heavily for many decades.
Hardware complexity is another question also, right?
Which one is more complex in hardware implement?
So I'm not going to answer a lot of these because this also goes into the implementation of the ISA,
not just the ISA itself.
But in general, data flow tends to be a bit harder.
OK, so here I will introduce a different level of trade off.
You can make this trade off at the ISA level.
You can say, oh, I want a program counter.
I don't want a program counter.
This is my execution model sequential versus data flow.
But you can say maybe I want my, I want to keep my ISA sequential because everybody in the world is
much more comfortable today with it.
But try to get the benefits of this data flow execution underneath at the micro architecture level.
So this here I will introduce this trade off at different parts.
So ISA specifies how the programmer sees the instructions to be executed, right?
It's really the hardware software interface micro architecture, which we will get into a little bit
more today and later.
It's really how the underlying implementation actually executes instructions.
Nobody said that micro architecture should do exactly the same thing ISA specifies, except for one
point.
The programmer needs to see what the ISA specifies because there's a contract, hardware, software
contract, and the processor or computing system you're building should obey that contract.
Otherwise programmers don't know what to do, right?
Otherwise people cannot write operating systems, compilers, whatever.
So you need to obey that interface, no question about that.
But underneath, as long as you obey that interface somehow internally, you can do many different
things right?
Internally, for example, whenever you're executing instructions, you don't need to execute 1
instruction at a time.
You can execute thousands of instructions at a time, but report back to the programmer as if you had
executed only one instruction at a time, right?
That's how you get high performance while preserving the hardware software interface that you are
bound with.
OK, so that's the idea over here.
So for I say, determines whether the programmer sees a sequential control flow execution order
versus a data flow execution order.
Micro architecture on the other hand, can execute an instruction in any order as the hardware
designer wants things to be executed, as long as the final results obeys the semantics specified by
the ISA when you make the instruction results visible to the software.
In other words, programmers should see the orders specified.
By the ISA, In other words, what we defined as architectural state in the past should not change in
a way that's inconsistent with the ISA.
OK, architectural state is what is visible to the programmer.
Memory registers PC.
Well, in this case you may not.
You may have PC.
Let's assume that you have a sequential execution model.
So all of those you cannot change, but internally you can do many, many other things.
And we'll see that all existing processors behave this way.
They have some sort of constraint in the contract, but internally they do something else to get high
performance.
Because if you actually execute the von Neumann model as is, you're executing 1 instruction at a
time, which is very poor in terms of performance.
If we were executing 1 instruction at a time, all of this AI stuff will not happen.
Basically, it happened because we had our hardware to actually train these models and fast do it
fast.
OK, OK, so we'll get back to the von Neumann model.
But if you learn to learn more about data flow, there's an old concept that has been examined and I
have some lecture videos on it if you're interested, much more detailed, like how do you do
function calls and data flow?
How do you deal with different data structures in data flow?
Very, very interesting things.
Any questions on data flow?
OK, let's talk about von Neumann model a little bit more.
So essentially all major instructions that architectures today use.
The von Neumann model, general purpose instructions and architectures, you may have seen some of
these names, but underneath at the micro architecture level, the execution model of almost all
implementations is very different, different from the what instruction set architecture specify.
OK, so for example, we do pipeline instruction execution.
As we will see, pipeline instruction execution means that whenever you're fetching an instruction,
you're decoding another one.
Whenever you're decoding another one, you're executing another one.
Whenever you're executing another one, you're you're actually doing memory access for another one,
etcetera.
So you're actually pipelining the execution of instruction and hardware.
This immediately violates the von Neumann model, right?
Von Neumann model says you are execute, you're supposed to execute only one instruction at a time.
You cannot move to the next instruction.
So pipelining violates this model, but we do it in all processors.
We do multiple instructions at a time.
Concurrent instructions, not like data flow, but you can do multiple.
You can fetch multiple instructions at a time and decode and execute.
That violates the von Neumann model.
We do auto order execution.
These are some of the earliest and more popular micro architectures that have introduced these and
we're going to see all of these.
Actually, multiple instructions at a time is called super scaler execution, not scaler, super
scaler.
As you can see, auto order execution means that you can execute, you can execute another instruction
that comes later in the instruction stream and you can do things out of order.
That clearly provides more performance and that actually takes advantage of some of the data flow
principles that we talked about.
As long as you don't update the programmer visible state with the results of those instructions,
right?
You update that programmer visible state as if you're doing things sequentially, but internally
you're doing things very parallel.
Things are going much faster than you would than they would be if you were doing things
sequentially, but you're reporting the results 1 by 1 as if the instructions are executed
sequentially.
We're going to talk about outer word execution again in lecture 15 or so.
We have separate instruction and data caches.
This also kind of violates the von Neumann model mildly because instruction and data are in a
unified memory, right?
OK, so basically you violate a lot of things, but what happens underneath that is not consistent
with the von Neumann model.
It's not exposed to the programmer or the software.
So they think that the machine is a von Neumann machine, right?
That's the interface.
And this is the key difference between ISA and micro architecture.
Basically, ISA is what is visible to the programmer, what they assume the machine will provide so
that they can program it.
But micro architecture is an implementation of the ISA.
It can, it can execute exactly like what von Neumann specified, 1 instruction at a time.
That's one implementation or it can do complete out of order execution, right?
So micro architecture is a specific implementation of an ISA basically.
So I've see I'm giving you this definition of computer architecture.
There are multiple definitions.
This is the ISA plus implementation definition.
It's the science and art of designing, selecting and interconnecting hardware components and design
the hardware software interface to create a computing system, which is important.
That means functional performance, energy consumption, cost and other specific goals.
But traditionally people have used this ISA only definition, which is not as you not much used
anymore.
But I'm going to talk about that a little bit more the term.
Architecture is used here to describe the attributes of a system as seen by the programmer.
OK, that was Gene Amdahl's definition when they designed IBM 360, which is a early processor that's
actually quite fast in its time in the 1960s.
Meaning the conceptual structure and functional behaviour as distinct from the organization of the
data flow and controls, the logic design and the physical implementation.
So this is part of this is micro architecture, data flow and controls, logic design, etcetera.
OK, so let's define these a little bit more carefully.
So this is the picture that I've shown you many times.
So ISA, micro architecture, microprocessor ISA is really the contract.
It's the agreed upon interface between software and hardware.
Or more more correctly, it's the book that's thrown at you by a manufacturer if you want to program
their processor.
That's the idea, right?
You can work with them to change that book, right?
But that's the book.
Basically, it's the contract.
So this is what the software or compiler or programmer assumes and this is what the hardware
promises, OK to provide.
In other words, it's what the software writer, any software writer needs to know to write and debug
user programs or system programs, OK, including compilers, operating systems, regular programs, any
program.
Basically, micro architecture is a specific implementation of that book of that contract
essentially, right?
It's not visible to the software.
Basically what is visible to the software is what that book specifies as visible to the software.
Micro architecture of course changes that, but what is done to change that is not visible to the
software.
OK.
Microprocessor today is defined as essentially all of those ISA, micro architecture and circuits
because ISA is a key part of micro architecture, Micro microprocessor also.
So people usually use the architecture term not in its purest form.
In 1960s, it's usually referred to as ISA plus micro architecture.
So people kind of abuse the term X86 architecture and then they also say Skylake architecture, for
example.
Yeah.
So don't get hung up on the, let's say lack of rigour and terminology.
That's just how it is.
OK, so let's talk about micro architecture a little bit because this is going to be what we will do
in the next N lectures, which is quite a few.
This is a specific implementation of the ISA.
Then the question becomes, how do we implement the ISA, right?
We will discuss this for many lectures.
And there can be many, many implementation of an ISA, for example, MIPS that your programming had
many, many implementations, including very wimpy simple ones, which is kind of similar to what
you're going to implement in your labs to very, very sophisticated ones which include auto order
execution, superscalar execution, many, many techniques that we're going to see.
There's also X86 that has many implementations.
POWER, IBM has many implementations.
ARM Alpha, RISC 5 these days has a lot of implementations.
And there's also other architectures like Z.
These are actually architectures that are quite interesting architectures, but they may not be
commonly used.
Z is, for example, IB, Ms.
architecture for a lot of banking systems in the world use these systems.
And these are huge systems that IBM sells for millions of dollars and they're not that big, you
know, still expensive.
You're not going to carry that in your pocket for sure.
They're big enough that you're not going to carry it in your pocket.
I guess you could carry it in your car if you're have that amount of money.
Well, I'll let you make that trade off.
OK, So ISA versus micro architecture.
One of the things that's good to talk about is what is part of the ISA versus micro architecture.
I like analogies and one of the best analogies that I have for this is really the gas pedal.
Although with self driving cars, things get blurred a little bit.
How many people drive cars here?
OK, trucks.
OK, some people, that's fine.
Yeah.
How many people drive self driving cars?
OK, I don't see any.
Interesting.
Why is that?
OK, OK.
Anyway, so basically as a driver, driver is a programmer, car is the hardware and implementation of
the car is micro architecture basically, right?
So there's an interface to drive this car, right?
And that interface is the ISA, in this case, instructions at architecture.
That's the architecture or instructions at architecture of the car.
You have a gas pedal.
Let's take one of them.
Gas pedal is the interface for acceleration, right?
That is specified.
You know exactly how it would behave, right?
You push.
It the car accelerates and there's a location also for that that's really important, you know,
because if you mess, mess it up, you may do the wrong thing.
You know, that location is important.
That's part of the interface.
And this interface doesn't change across many cars, right?
But internally the implementation of that acceleration can be very different across different cars,
right?
That's the internals of the engine, right?
Some of them may be very automated, right, very controlled by microprocessors.
Some of them may be much more powerful than others, right?
Some of them may be, I don't know the Mr.
Bean's car, he has a different way of accelerating maybe I don't know, right.
So basically there are many different ways of implementing that engine, right?
But the gas pedal doesn't change, interface doesn't change or at least there are not that many
interfaces.
OK, so that's I think a good analogy to think about ISA versus micro architecture.
Meaning micro architecture or implementation can be various as long as it satisfies the
specification.
If someone wants to give you a specification where the gas pedal is like in your hand, then that's a
different specification.
You need to learn it.
It can be implemented with somewhat similar internals.
Micro architecture may be similar, but then you need to program it differently.
You need to use it differently, right?
The same is true for the clutch or whatever you're using to change gears.
So you can actually expand the analogy.
And some of those, some of those Isas are different.
Actually, some cars have the shifting gear here on the right around the steering wheel, right?
I don't drive cars that much, so I'm happy not to drive anyway.
And some cars have it over here, right?
And if you're looking for it in the wrong place, you may have an accident.
OK, so in the hardware we have similar things, right?
You have an ADD instruction.
We've specified the semantics of the ADD instruction in the ISA.
But you may have many implementation of the adder, right?
Adder can be a ripple carry adder, Adder can be carry.
Look at adder and many different type of adders people have done.
And yeah, we've covered some of them.
There's also a bit serial adders.
You bit, you add one bit at a time every clock cycle.
If you want to add 32 bits, you need 32 clock cycles.
We didn't cover this that much, but you can imagine that sort of adder.
Also.
Similarly, XA6 has many implementations, but XA6 ISA doesn't change that much.
Basically, micro architecture usually changes faster than the ISA.
There are few IS as but many many many many micro architectures, right?
Over time, micro architectures evolve.
They add new instructions, but they normally don't remove instructions.
Why is that?
Can anybody guess why ISA doesn't change as much?
Yes, exactly.
Yeah, so you use 2 words that may be cryptic for many people, but backwards compatibility, meaning
people write programs assuming that ISA.
And if you actually change the ISA completely, those programs may not execute very well in your new
processor, right?
So you need to actually keep the ISA same.
You can add new things so that people can write new instructions.
That's fine.
But if you start removing instructions, for example, and changing the ISA significantly, people will
be very unhappy because their programs will not run on your new hardware.
OK.
That's why it's difficult to change the ISA.
We'll have more stories about that when people have tried to change the ISAS.
Similar to gas pedal, right?
You decide, oh, I want to put the gas pedal to the left of the brake or right of the brake today or
in my next car.
See how many people buy that car.
I guess it's a good experiment to do if you want to lose money, probably.
OK, So what does ISA specify?
Many things, actually.
It's more than instructions.
We've seen instructions.
We've seen memory.
We're going to see a lot more.
We're going to see more things like interrupt exception handling, like what happens when you cannot
execute an instruction?
Right.
ISA specifies that.
Also, access control, who can access what location ISA specifies it.
Also, how do you deal with IO devices?
How do you deal with tasks and threads?
How do you deal with power management, thermal management?
How do you deal with errors?
How do you deal with multiple processors?
We're going to talk about a lot of those later on.
But this manual, as you can see, well, maybe this one you can see a few years ago it was 5000 pages.
It's good bedtime reading.
If you're interested in reading the stuff then it keeps getting extended.
ARM is supposed to be a simpler ISA but it's competing as you can see.
5000 plus pages also here.
So a good bedtime reading if you're interested.
RISC 5 claims to be a simpler ISA but it's going to be 5000 pages if it's not already 5000 pages.
OK, so micro architecture.
There's really an implementation of the ISA under specific design constraints and goals, anything
done in hardware without exposure to software basically.
So there are many things that we're going to cover pipelining in order versus out of order
execution.
I'm not going to cover all of these right now, but for example, clock gating, when you're not using
part of the hardware, existing machines turn clock off so that you don't waste energy, waste power.
So this is something that's done without the programmer's knowledge, right?
You could also make it visible to the programmer.
You could basically add an instruction to the ISA saying clock gates.
And people have proposed things like that, but it's very difficult to control these things.
Error correction is another example.
OK, we're going to see some of these, but let's have some fun right now.
This is actually a good exam practice also.
So which one is a property of the ISA versus a property of the micro architecture?
Based on what we said?
Is this ISA or micro architecture add instructions opcode.
Who says ISA?
OK, who says micro architecture?
OK, nobody that's good, or at least I don't see the hands.
Yes, this is ISA because opcode needs to be specified so that the programmer can write a program,
right that can be executed on the machine type of adder used in the ALU, whether it's bit serial or
ripple carry.
Is this part of ISA or micro architecture?
Who says ISA?
Who says micro architecture?
OK, that's good.
I think we got it.
Maybe it'll become harder and harder.
The number of general purpose registers.
ISA, micro architecture.
OK, ISA wins.
General purpose registers need to be specified because they're part of the instruction and coding,
right?
Internally that may be different, but we'll talk about that later.
Number of cycles to execute the multiply instruction.
Who says ISA?
Who says micro architecture?
OK, micro architecture wins in this case, which is the majority because number of cycles is an
implementation thing.
ISA normally specifies multiply.
That said, some I you can change the ISA, of course.
You can write your own book that says I have a multiply with five cycles and the programmer assumes
that they write code assuming that and then you change the multiply to three cycles, you give them
another book and then you're causing problems, right.
Yes, not necessarily recommendations, but they may actually that book may say OK in this particular
micro architecture, it's 3 cycles, right.
So ISA is also this these books usually it's actually not just the ISA, it's also soft.
It's called the software developers and optimisers manual and knowing the number of cycles may be
helpful, but they do not specify it as part of the instruction.
They specify it as part of on this micro architecture like Skylake, it takes 3 cycles.
So if you're optimising for Skylake, do it, but we don't guarantee anything for any other micro
architecture.
OK, OK, Number of ports of the register file, ISA or micro architecture.
Who says ISA?
Who says micro architecture?
OK, micro architecture wins here again because number of ports of the register file is an
implementation choice as we will see.
ISA specifies how many registers you access for a given instruction, but you could actually have
thousands of ports of the register file if you want, or only one port and do it in multiple cycles,
for example, right?
OK, yeah, I think this is micro architecture.
I'll give it to you program counter.
Is that ISA or micro architecture, which is ISA?
OK, micro architecture, OK, it's ISAI made it hard for a lot of some people, but OK, you'll study it
and figure it out.
Remember basically the key is micro architecture is implementation of the ISA under specific design
constraints and goals.
Program counter is is part of the execution model.
Actually it is specified in that book, right?
For example, branch instruction changes the program counter this way.
Some other instruction changed the program counter this way.
It specifies how the instructions operate.
So the programmer needs to know this.
OK, so let's talk about design point.
Design point is also important because when we design A processor, which we're going to do in the
next end lectures, it's good to, you're always designing a processor for a particular purpose,
right?
You have a set of design considerations and you have a priority of or level of their importance.
This leads to trade-offs in both in structured architectures as well as micro architectures.
Now in structured architectures, if you can design instructions and architectures of course, right.
So there are many considerations here.
Cost, performance, maximum power consumption, thermal limits, energy consumption, availability of
the system or.
You can think of it as mean time to failure.
When does it fail?
What is the average time the system will be up, reliability and correctness, time to market, Many,
many things basically.
I, I could add more over here, but I'm not going to do that.
Privacy is for example, another one.
So this design point is really determined by what you're targeting.
What is the problem that you're trying to solve?
What are the applications or the intended users and market, right?
If it's a hyper, if it's a let's say high performance computer that's going to execute only
scientific simulations, that is a very different design point than a mobile phone in my pocket,
right?
Which is a very different design point than a than a machine learning accelerator that's going to
execute only large language model inference that comes from many, many users.
OK, So there is actually design point determines how you design the microprocessor application space
clearly determines a lot of things and this has never been a problem.
People have always come up come up with good applications.
I'd recommend this very nice paper from my PhD advisor, Yale Pat that was in 2001 that talks about
essentially how microprocessors evolved.
It's a bit dated, but the key principles are actually.
Very good over there.
And here is a quote from that base.
There are many different types of applications, right?
You may be designing for different one of them, you may be designing a general purpose processor and
you may be designing for all of them.
Then your task is much harder, right?
You cannot optimise for any single one easily.
And there are many other workloads today, especially over here.
You can see we do a lot of work on genome analysis, for example, machine learning, graph analytics.
These are actually really difficult workloads sometimes graph analytics being probably one of the
most difficult ones.
OK, so basically people keep generating new applications, applications push boundaries.
Computing platforms actually are becoming increasingly constrained.
So we're going to see general purpose models first in these lectures.
We're going to start with a very basic processor and then we're going to improve it to be higher and
higher performance, but we're going to keep general purpose.
And then we're going to examine things like GPUs, for example, which are designed to be special
purpose and they became a little bit more general purpose and they're becoming a little bit more
special purpose right now also with machine learning.
But they're also relatively general purpose, but less general purpose than CPUs.
And we're going to then talk about accelerators, like how machine learning accelerators are
designed.
So application space and how you want to design the processor for that application space determines
the trade-offs you can make, right?
So these trade-offs are actually the real soul of computer architecture And this sort of course,
basically, and this is really the critical part in my opinion, it's important to think critically
in all of these trade-offs because you have a lot of assuming that you're designing A computing
system.
Let's say, let's say you, you have your, you had the good fortune to be hired as a chief architect
of or you, you start your own company and you want to actually design your own computer, right?
Which is a difficult task.
And you have all the freedom in the world, right?
Where do you start?
So you really need to start making trade-offs.
You need to decide an ISA or you decide your own ISA and you figure out what are the trade-offs
associated with it, right?
And then you need to implement the ISA.
There are micro architecture level trade-offs that you need to make, which we're going to see a lot
of them.
You need to design your execution model, of course, with the ISA together with the ISA.
And then there's also system and test level trade-offs, which we didn't talk a whole lot about, but
we did actually start this lecture with which is really the where you place the ISA and where you
put the different tasks.
Do you put them in software?
Do you put them in hardware?
So essentially a computer architecture is really the, this is the broader definition.
It's really the science and art of making the appropriate trade off to meet a design point.
That's where the design point comes in, right?
The application space, right?
If your application space is accelerating only matrix multiplication, your task is a bit easier,
right?
If your application space is whatever people throw at me, your task is much harder, right?
Especially if you want to get high performance, energy efficiency, etcetera.
I've also mentioned that I say science and art all the time, right?
Some scientists don't like that because we don't think art has any place in science.
I completely disagree.
Art has a huge place in science because we don't know everything in the world and we cannot model
everything in the world, right?
So basically you're designing this thing, but this thing is not in isolation.
Basically, you don't know the full future, right?
You may think matrix multiplication done in some way is what you're designing for, but two years
later, somebody's going to do something else, right?
And you cannot control that.
You cannot model that as far as, at least currently, we don't know how to model the future.
If you know that, that'd be great.
Let me know if you know that.
OK?
So basically, you don't know the applications, you don't know the users, you don't know the market
exactly.
You can.
Have a guess and people who are successful that make very good guesses, right?
So basically it's art in the end.
And also things change.
At the top, people have different problems to solve.
There are new issues and capabilities.
At the bottom.
You may design an architecture using some technology and then that technology becomes obsolete.
Too high power and then you will need to do something else and think users change also.
Basically you cannot predict.
Future is also not constant, right?
Basically changes, people have changing demands, etcetera.
So I'd like this analogue for macro architecture.
I haven't done a lot of analogues from micro architecture in this class yet, but I'll do some.
So future is not constant in macro architecture.
There are a lot of similarities in real architecture, real meaning building type of architecture and
computer architecture.
So for example, people have used buildings designed for purpose X for some other purpose.
So there's another, this is from Zurich, for example.
If you've been to this mill, which was originally a brewery, it became something else right?
Now, right?
Over time, basically things change, right?
Even though the structure may not, may not change that much, right?
The application changes, but the application may not fit it very well, right?
It's good to think about that.
Also, maybe this doesn't bother us that much, but it bothers things much more with programmers.
I like this one.
Also.
You know, there's a coffee shop right now in Zurich.
It's used originally by EWZI.
Guess this is my favorite example from Pittsburgh, which I will be going to next week for a
conference.
I used to live there, but in the in the Zurich case, brewery became something else.
In this case, a church became a brewery.
So if you go to Pittsburgh, I'd recommend going there.
It's a church brew works.
OK.
So that's the end of this lecture.
I'd recommend you take a look at assembly programming.
Tomorrow we will start with micro architecture.